<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" version="3" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-perkins-irtf-code-of-conduct-08" number="9775" updates="" obsoletes="" category="info" submissionType="IRTF" tocInclude="true" sortRefs="true" symRefs="true" xml:lang="en" prepTime="2025-03-18T20:52:47" indexInclude="true" scripts="Common,Latin" tocDepth="3">
  <link href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-perkins-irtf-code-of-conduct-08" rel="prev"/>
  <link href="https://dx.doi.org/10.17487/rfc9775" rel="alternate"/>
  <link href="urn:issn:2070-1721" rel="alternate"/>
  <front>
    <title abbrev="IRTF Code of Conduct">IRTF Code of Conduct</title>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9775" stream="IRTF"/>
    <author initials="C. S." surname="Perkins" fullname="Colin Perkins">
      <organization showOnFrontPage="true">University of Glasgow</organization>
      <address>
        <email>csp@csperkins.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="03" year="2025"/>
    <keyword>IRTF</keyword>
    <keyword>Code of Conduct</keyword>
    <abstract pn="section-abstract">
      <t indent="0" pn="section-abstract-1">This document describes the code of conduct for participants in the
Internet Research Task Force (IRTF).</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-abstract-2">The IRTF believes that research is most effective when done in an open
and inclusive forum that encourages diversity of ideas and 
participation.
Through this code of conduct, the IRTF continues to strive to create
and maintain an environment that encourages broad participation, and one
in which people are treated with dignity, decency, and respect.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-abstract-3">This document is a product of the Internet Research Steering Group (IRSG).</t>
    </abstract>
    <boilerplate>
      <section anchor="status-of-memo" numbered="false" removeInRFC="false" toc="exclude" pn="section-boilerplate.1">
        <name slugifiedName="name-status-of-this-memo">Status of This Memo</name>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-boilerplate.1-1">
            This document is not an Internet Standards Track specification; it is
            published for informational purposes.
        </t>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-boilerplate.1-2">
            This document is a product of the Internet Research Task Force
            (IRTF).  The IRTF publishes the results of Internet-related
            research and development activities.  These results might not be
            suitable for deployment.  Documents approved for publication by the
            IRSG are not candidates for any level of Internet Standard; see
            Section 2 of RFC 7841.
        </t>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-boilerplate.1-3">
            Information about the current status of this document, any
            errata, and how to provide feedback on it may be obtained at
            <eref target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc9775" brackets="none"/>.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="copyright" numbered="false" removeInRFC="false" toc="exclude" pn="section-boilerplate.2">
        <name slugifiedName="name-copyright-notice">Copyright Notice</name>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-boilerplate.2-1">
            Copyright (c) 2025 IETF Trust and the persons identified as the
            document authors. All rights reserved.
        </t>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-boilerplate.2-2">
            This document is subject to BCP 78 and the IETF Trust's Legal
            Provisions Relating to IETF Documents
            (<eref target="https://trustee.ietf.org/license-info" brackets="none"/>) in effect on the date of
            publication of this document. Please review these documents
            carefully, as they describe your rights and restrictions with
            respect to this document.
        </t>
      </section>
    </boilerplate>
    <toc>
      <section anchor="toc" numbered="false" removeInRFC="false" toc="exclude" pn="section-toc.1">
        <name slugifiedName="name-table-of-contents">Table of Contents</name>
        <ul bare="true" empty="true" indent="2" spacing="compact" pn="section-toc.1-1">
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.1">
            <t indent="0" keepWithNext="true" pn="section-toc.1-1.1.1"><xref derivedContent="1" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-1"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-introduction">Introduction</xref></t>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.2">
            <t indent="0" keepWithNext="true" pn="section-toc.1-1.2.1"><xref derivedContent="2" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-2"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-rationale">Rationale</xref></t>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.3">
            <t indent="0" keepWithNext="true" pn="section-toc.1-1.3.1"><xref derivedContent="3" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-3"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-conduct">Conduct</xref></t>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.4">
            <t indent="0" pn="section-toc.1-1.4.1"><xref derivedContent="4" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-4"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-research-integrity">Research Integrity</xref></t>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.5">
            <t indent="0" pn="section-toc.1-1.5.1"><xref derivedContent="5" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-5"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-research-ethics">Research Ethics</xref></t>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.6">
            <t indent="0" pn="section-toc.1-1.6.1"><xref derivedContent="6" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-6"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-inclusive-language-and-imag">Inclusive Language and Imagery</xref></t>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.7">
            <t indent="0" pn="section-toc.1-1.7.1"><xref derivedContent="7" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-7"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-participation-and-accessibi">Participation and Accessibility</xref></t>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.8">
            <t indent="0" pn="section-toc.1-1.8.1"><xref derivedContent="8" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-8"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-security-considerations">Security Considerations</xref></t>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.9">
            <t indent="0" pn="section-toc.1-1.9.1"><xref derivedContent="9" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-9"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-iana-considerations">IANA Considerations</xref></t>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.10">
            <t indent="0" pn="section-toc.1-1.10.1"><xref derivedContent="10" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-10"/>. <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-references">References</xref></t>
            <ul bare="true" empty="true" indent="2" spacing="compact" pn="section-toc.1-1.10.2">
              <li pn="section-toc.1-1.10.2.1">
                <t indent="0" pn="section-toc.1-1.10.2.1.1"><xref derivedContent="10.1" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-10.1"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-normative-references">Normative References</xref></t>
              </li>
              <li pn="section-toc.1-1.10.2.2">
                <t indent="0" pn="section-toc.1-1.10.2.2.1"><xref derivedContent="10.2" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-10.2"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-informative-references">Informative References</xref></t>
              </li>
            </ul>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.11">
            <t indent="0" pn="section-toc.1-1.11.1"><xref derivedContent="" format="none" sectionFormat="of" target="section-appendix.a"/><xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-acknowledgments">Acknowledgments</xref></t>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.12">
            <t indent="0" pn="section-toc.1-1.12.1"><xref derivedContent="" format="none" sectionFormat="of" target="section-appendix.b"/><xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-authors-address">Author's Address</xref></t>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </section>
    </toc>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="introduction" numbered="true" removeInRFC="false" toc="include" pn="section-1">
      <name slugifiedName="name-introduction">Introduction</name>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-1-1">The Internet Research Task Force (IRTF) promotes research of importance
to the evolution and deployment of the Internet protocols, applications,
architecture and technology, and to understand the development of the
Internet in all its diversity and for all its users, considering the
technical, economic, and societal challenges of such development.
The IRTF focuses on longer-term research issues related to the Internet
while the parallel organisation, the Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF),
focuses on the shorter-term issues of engineering and standards-making.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-1-2">The IRTF believes that research is most effective when done in an open
and inclusive forum that encourages diversity of ideas and 
participation.
Through this code of conduct, the IRTF will continue to strive to create
and maintain an environment that encourages broad participation, and one
in which people are treated with dignity, decency, and respect.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-1-3">This document was developed by the Internet Research Steering Group (IRSG) with broad consultation and review from the IRTF community. It represents the consensus of the Internet Research Steering
Group (IRSG).  It is not an IETF product and is not a standard.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="rationale" numbered="true" removeInRFC="false" toc="include" pn="section-2">
      <name slugifiedName="name-rationale">Rationale</name>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-2-1">The IRTF is not the IETF. While the two organisations work closely
together, and often co-locate meetings and other activities, they have
different goals and work in different ways.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-2-2">The IETF is a consensus-driven standards-developing organisation, where
participants use their best engineering judgment to find the best solution
for the whole Internet as it stands today, and to develop the best
technical standards to make the Internet work better.
IRTF research can be more speculative, and takes a longer-term view of
the development of the Internet without the requirements for consensus
or near-term applicability and deployability that come from standards
development. A further discussion of the differences between IRTF and
IETF can be found in <xref target="RFC7418" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC7418"/>.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-2-3">Compared to the IETF equivalent <xref target="RFC7154" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC7154"/>, this IRTF code of conduct
reflects those differences in emphasis between the two organisations.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="conduct" numbered="true" removeInRFC="false" toc="include" pn="section-3">
      <name slugifiedName="name-conduct">Conduct</name>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-3-1">The IRTF is committed to providing a safe and equitable experience for all
participants. Those participating in the IRTF must extend respect and
courtesy to others at all times.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-3-2">Harassment is behaviour that is unwelcome, hostile, or intimidating.
Harassment includes, in particular, speech or behaviour that is sexually
aggressive or that intimidates based on attributes such as education, race,
gender, religion, age, colour, national origin, ancestry, disability,
medical condition, sexual orientation, or gender identity <xref target="RFC7776" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC7776"/>.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-3-3">Examples of harassment
include, but are not limited to, the use of offensive language or sexual
imagery, degrading verbal comments,
deliberate intimidation, stalking, harassing photography or recording,
inappropriate physical contact, and unwelcome sexual attention.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-3-4">Harassment will not be tolerated in IRTF research group meetings, open
meetings, conferences, workshops, other events, mailing lists, virtual meetings, or other online
forums. Participants must follow the IETF anti-harassment policy, which also
applies to the IRTF <xref target="ANTI-HARASSMENT" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="ANTI-HARASSMENT"/>.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-3-5">Participants who believe they have been harassed, notice that someone else is being
harassed, or have any other concerns relating to potential harassment or
conduct, are encouraged to raise their
concern with the relevant research group chair or the IRTF Chair, or with the
Ombudsteam <xref target="OMBUDSTEAM" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="OMBUDSTEAM"/> who work on an independent and confidential basis.
All such concerns will be seriously considered and action will be taken as
appropriate, up to and including the exclusion of the offending party from IRTF
activities.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-3-6">The IRTF sometimes organises meetings or activities that co-locate with
events organised by others. These meetings or activities may need to follow
the anti-harassment policy of the hosting event, which may differ from that
of the IRTF. In such cases, the organisers of the IRTF meeting or activity
should check with the IRTF Chair to confirm that the policy is acceptable
and it should be made clear to participants what policy applies.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-3-7">The IRTF operates and makes use of a number of mailing lists and other
online discussion forums. At the time of this writing, research group
chairs act as moderators for such forums used by their research groups,
and the IRTF Chair moderates IRTF-wide lists and discussion forums.
Other moderators may be appointed in the future.
   Harassment or disruption on these lists and discussion forums
   due to posting messages that are
   inflammatory, abusive, or otherwise inappropriate, or due to the repeated
   posting of off-topic material, will not be tolerated.
Moderators will respond to harassing or disruptive behaviour with either a
warning, by temporarily suspending posting rights, or after approval from
the IRTF Chair by permanently suspending posting rights for an individual,
based on the seriousness and history of the behaviour.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-3-8">Participants who have concerns about, or wish to appeal against, a moderation decision
should raise their concerns with the IRTF Chair. If
the concern relates to moderation decisions taken by the IRTF Chair, then it
should be raised with the Internet Architecture Board.
These parties will review the situation and may reverse the
moderation decision or take other action as appropriate.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="research-integrity" numbered="true" removeInRFC="false" toc="include" pn="section-4">
      <name slugifiedName="name-research-integrity">Research Integrity</name>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-4-1">Participants must act with respect, honesty, transparency, and fairness.
They should be trustworthy, aspire to objectivity, and aim to provide factual
evidence in support of their claims and justification for their reasoning.
They should be generous, give credit to others where it is due, and
recognise that understanding advances through collaborative research
efforts of many, rather than for the glory of a few.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-4-2">Plagiarism, misrepresentation of authorship, and
content falsification constitute dishonesty and fraud. Such actions are
prohibited and the IRTF may take action against authors who commit them,
including retraction of the published work or exclusion of the offending
party from IRTF activities.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-4-3">Generative artificial intelligence (AI) tools and systems must not be listed as authors of IRTF
documents, presentations, or other materials. The use of generative AI
to create text or other content is permitted but must be disclosed if
significant amounts of such content are included, for
example through an acknowledgement describing which AI system was used and
how it contributed.  The use of AI to perform spelling or grammar checks
and corrections, to translate between languages, or to otherwise improve
the presentation of content need not be disclosed.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-4-4">The IRTF publishes informational and experimental documents in the RFC
series. The nature of these documents, and their preceding Internet-Drafts,
is that they often extend or elaborate upon previously published research
results, to support ongoing development and experimentation by the IRTF
community. These documents are
encouraged as an important part of the process of disseminating
research ideas and ensuring that they work in the Internet at large.
Authors must ensure that prior work, including their own prior work,
is appropriately cited and acknowledged, and that new documents
respect the copyright of prior work and are written with the
permission of any coauthors.
</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-4-5">IRTF documents may represent the views of their authors or they may be
consensus documents representing the views of a research group. It is a
misrepresentation for authors to falsely claim that a document represents
the consensus view of a research group.  Similarly, the editors of a
research group consensus document must not misrepresent their role as that
of authors.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="research-ethics" numbered="true" removeInRFC="false" toc="include" pn="section-5">
      <name slugifiedName="name-research-ethics">Research Ethics</name>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-5-1">Participants must ensure that their research, in particular research that
involves human subjects or personal data, is conducted ethically and with
respect for persons, in careful consideration of the risks and benefits
of the work,
taking care to ensure that those who bear the risk also gain some benefit,
and with respect for the law and public interest.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-5-2">Participants should consult with their organisation's Institutional Review
Board, Research Ethics Committee, or similar, prior to conducting research
that might raise ethical concerns.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-5-3">Participants are referred to the guidance in the Menlo Report <xref target="MENLO" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="MENLO"/>, the
Belmont Report <xref target="BELMONT" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="BELMONT"/>, and the ACM Policy on Research Involving Human
Participants and Subjects <xref target="ACM" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="ACM"/> for further discussion of issues around
ethical conduct of research.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="inclusive-language-and-imagery" numbered="true" removeInRFC="false" toc="include" pn="section-6">
      <name slugifiedName="name-inclusive-language-and-imag">Inclusive Language and Imagery</name>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-6-1">Participants should ensure that language and imagery used in IRTF
documents, presentations, mailing lists, research group meetings, open meetings,
conferences, workshops, and other events, are respectful and inclusive.
Effective research uses terminology that is clear, precise, and widely
accessible to readers from varying backgrounds and cultures.  Participants
are encouraged to follow the guidance on inclusive language in <xref target="NISTIR8366" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="NISTIR8366"/>
when making contributions to the IRTF <xref target="INCLUSIVE" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="INCLUSIVE"/>.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-6-2">
  Participants should avoid the use of slang and unnecessary jargon in
  both spoken and written communication. When
  communication difficulties arise, IRTF participants should make a
  sincere effort to understand each other and to engage in conversation
  to clarify when necessary.
</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="participation-and-accessibility" numbered="true" removeInRFC="false" toc="include" pn="section-7">
      <name slugifiedName="name-participation-and-accessibi">Participation and Accessibility</name>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-7-1">To encourage broad participation and support the goal of providing an
open and inclusive forum that promotes diversity of ideas and 
participation, IRTF participants
should consider accessibility and access-related concerns when organising
research group meetings, open meetings, conferences, workshops, and other events to
ensure such events are broadly accessible to all who wish to participate.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-7-2">English is the de facto language in which the IRTF works, but it is not the
native language of many IRTF participants. All participants, particularly
those with English as a first language, should attempt to accommodate the
needs of others by communicating clearly.
Reading, writing, and conversing in a language where one is not a native
speaker may be difficult, and IRTF participants should treat those doing
so with grace and understanding.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-7-3">Participants should aim to speak slowly and clearly in presentations and
discussions, and they should strive to make presentations and other materials
accessible to those with impaired vision or disabilities.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-7-4">Participants should work to enable remote participation in IRTF events to
support those who cannot attend in person, and they should aim to make materials
available online in a timely and broadly accessible manner.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-7-5">The IRTF will work to provide travel grants, fee waivers, childcare, and
other support to help participation by students, early career researchers,
members of under-represented groups, those with disabilities, and others
who might otherwise be unable to participate. Participants are encouraged
to make use of these opportunities.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-7-6">IRTF research groups may have open or limited membership <xref target="RFC2014" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC2014"/>.
Limited membership may be advantageous to the formation of the long-term
working relationships that are critical to successful collaborative research.
However, limited membership must be used with care and sensitivity to avoid
unnecessary fragmentation of the work of the research community.
The charter of each research group defines its membership policy (whether
open or limited) and the procedure to apply for membership in the group.
While limited membership is permitted, it is in no way encouraged or required.
Research group chairs must enforce the membership policy of their group in
a fair and transparent manner, providing a clear rationale for their decisions.
Participants with concerns about the administration of the membership policy
for a research group, or who wish to appeal a membership decision, should
raise their concern with the IRTF Chair.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-7-7">In exceptional cases, advice from legal counsel may be to restrict an
individual from using IRTF IT systems and/or from participating in IRTF
research group meetings, open meetings, conferences, workshops, and other
events. In such cases, the IRTF Chair will act following the principles outlined in the
Statement on Restricting Access <xref target="RESTRICTING" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RESTRICTING"/>. Due to the potential impact
on the standards process, arising from the use of shared infrastructure and
joint meetings between the IRTF and IETF, any such action by the IRTF Chair
will only be taken in consultation with the IESG.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="security-considerations" numbered="true" removeInRFC="false" toc="include" pn="section-8">
      <name slugifiedName="name-security-considerations">Security Considerations</name>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-8-1">This IRTF code of conduct does not directly affect the security of the
Internet.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-8-2">Research results, when translated into practice, have the potential to
significantly impact the security and privacy of users of the Internet.
Researchers should consider the potential security benefits, risks, and
implications of their work and, where possible, should aim to improve
security and protect the privacy of Internet users through their research
<xref target="RFC8890" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC8890"/>.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="iana-considerations" numbered="true" removeInRFC="false" toc="include" pn="section-9">
      <name slugifiedName="name-iana-considerations">IANA Considerations</name>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-9-1">This document has no IANA actions.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references anchor="sec-combined-references" pn="section-10">
      <name slugifiedName="name-references">References</name>
      <references anchor="sec-normative-references" pn="section-10.1">
        <name slugifiedName="name-normative-references">Normative References</name>
        <reference anchor="ANTI-HARASSMENT" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/statement-iesg-ietf-anti-harassment-policy-20131103/" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="ANTI-HARASSMENT">
          <front>
            <title>IETF Anti-Harassment Policy</title>
            <author>
              <organization showOnFrontPage="true">IETF</organization>
            </author>
            <date month="November" year="2013"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="INCLUSIVE" target="https://irtf.org/policies/inclusive-language.html" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="INCLUSIVE">
          <front>
            <title>Inclusive Language in Contributions to the IRTF</title>
            <author>
              <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
            </author>
            <date year="2021" month="May"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="NISTIR8366" target="https://web.archive.org/web/20250203031433/https://nvlpubs.nist.gov/nistpubs/ir/2021/NIST.IR.8366.pdf" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="NISTIR8366">
          <front>
            <title>Guidance for NIST Staff on Using Inclusive Language in Documentary Standards</title>
            <author>
              <organization showOnFrontPage="true">National Institute of Standards and Technology</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2021" month="April"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.6028/NIST.IR.8366"/>
          <refcontent>Interagency or Internal Report 8366 (NISTIR 8366)</refcontent>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="OMBUDSTEAM" target="https://www.ietf.org/contact/ombudsteam/" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="OMBUDSTEAM">
          <front>
            <title>Ombudsteam</title>
            <author>
              <organization showOnFrontPage="true">IETF</organization>
            </author>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="RESTRICTING" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/statement-iesg-statement-on-restricting-access-to-ietf-it-systems-20221031/" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="RESTRICTING">
          <front>
            <title>Statement on Restricting Access to IETF IT Systems</title>
            <author>
              <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
            </author>
            <date year="2022" month="October"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="RFC2014" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc2014" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="RFC2014">
          <front>
            <title>IRTF Research Group Guidelines and Procedures</title>
            <author fullname="A. Weinrib" initials="A." surname="Weinrib"/>
            <author fullname="J. Postel" initials="J." surname="Postel"/>
            <date month="October" year="1996"/>
            <abstract>
              <t indent="0">This document describes the guidelines and procedures for formation and operation of IRTF Research Groups. It describes the relationship between IRTF participants, Research Groups, the Internet Research Steering Group (IRSG) and the Internet Architecture Board (IAB). This document specifies an Internet Best Current Practices for the Internet Community, and requests discussion and suggestions for improvements.</t>
            </abstract>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="8"/>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2014"/>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC2014"/>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="RFC7154" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7154" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="RFC7154">
          <front>
            <title>IETF Guidelines for Conduct</title>
            <author fullname="S. Moonesamy" initials="S." role="editor" surname="Moonesamy"/>
            <date month="March" year="2014"/>
            <abstract>
              <t indent="0">This document provides a set of guidelines for personal interaction in the Internet Engineering Task Force. The guidelines recognize the diversity of IETF participants, emphasize the value of mutual respect, and stress the broad applicability of our work.</t>
              <t indent="0">This document is an updated version of the guidelines for conduct originally published in RFC 3184.</t>
            </abstract>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="54"/>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="7154"/>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC7154"/>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="RFC7418" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7418" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="RFC7418">
          <front>
            <title>An IRTF Primer for IETF Participants</title>
            <author fullname="S. Dawkins" initials="S." role="editor" surname="Dawkins"/>
            <date month="December" year="2014"/>
            <abstract>
              <t indent="0">This document provides a high-level description of things for Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF) participants to consider when bringing proposals for new research groups (RGs) into the Internet Research Task Force (IRTF). This document emphasizes differences in expectations between the two organizations.</t>
            </abstract>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="7418"/>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC7418"/>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="RFC7776" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7776" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="RFC7776">
          <front>
            <title>IETF Anti-Harassment Procedures</title>
            <author fullname="P. Resnick" initials="P." surname="Resnick"/>
            <author fullname="A. Farrel" initials="A." surname="Farrel"/>
            <date month="March" year="2016"/>
            <abstract>
              <t indent="0">IETF Participants must not engage in harassment while at IETF meetings, virtual meetings, or social events or while participating in mailing lists. This document lays out procedures for managing and enforcing this policy.</t>
              <t indent="0">This document updates RFC 2418 by defining new working group guidelines and procedures. This document updates RFC 7437 by allowing the Ombudsteam to form a recall petition without further signatories.</t>
            </abstract>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="25"/>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="7776"/>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC7776"/>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="RFC8890" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8890" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="RFC8890">
          <front>
            <title>The Internet is for End Users</title>
            <author fullname="M. Nottingham" initials="M." surname="Nottingham"/>
            <date month="August" year="2020"/>
            <abstract>
              <t indent="0">This document explains why the IAB believes that, when there is a conflict between the interests of end users of the Internet and other parties, IETF decisions should favor end users. It also explores how the IETF can more effectively achieve this.</t>
            </abstract>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8890"/>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8890"/>
        </reference>
      </references>
      <references anchor="sec-informative-references" pn="section-10.2">
        <name slugifiedName="name-informative-references">Informative References</name>
        <reference anchor="ACM" target="https://www.acm.org/publications/policies/research-involving-human-participants-and-subjects" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="ACM">
          <front>
            <title>ACM Publications Policy on Research Involving Human Participants and Subjects</title>
            <author>
              <organization showOnFrontPage="true">ACM Publications Board</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2021" month="August"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="BELMONT" target="https://www.hhs.gov/ohrp/regulations-and-policy/belmont-report/" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="BELMONT">
          <front>
            <title>The Belmont Report - Ethical Principles and Guidelines for the Protection of Human Subjects of Research</title>
            <author>
              <organization showOnFrontPage="true">National Commission for the Protection of Human Subjects of Biomedical and Behavioral Research</organization>
            </author>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="MENLO" target="https://www.dhs.gov/sites/default/files/publications/CSD-MenloPrinciplesCORE-20120803_1.pdf" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="MENLO">
          <front>
            <title>The Menlo Report - Ethical Principles Guiding Information and Communication Technology Research</title>
            <author>
              <organization showOnFrontPage="true">US Department of Homeland Security Science and Technology Directorate</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2012" month="August"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
      </references>
    </references>
    <section numbered="false" anchor="acknowledgments" removeInRFC="false" toc="include" pn="section-appendix.a">
      <name slugifiedName="name-acknowledgments">Acknowledgments</name>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-appendix.a-1">This work is supported in part by the UK Engineering and Physical Sciences
Research Council under grant EP/S036075/1.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-appendix.a-2">This document is based, in part, on the IETF guidelines for conduct <xref target="RFC7154" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC7154"/>.
The influence of the code of conduct and other policies of ICANN, the USENIX
Association, and the Association for Computing Machinery is also gratefully
acknowledged.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-appendix.a-3">Thanks to <contact fullname="Carsten Bormann"/>, <contact fullname="Vigdis Bronder"/>, <contact fullname="Laurent Ciavaglia"/>,
      <contact fullname="Ignacio Castro"/>, <contact fullname="Jane Coffin"/>,
      <contact fullname="Jay Daley"/>, <contact fullname="Dhruv Dhody"/>,
      <contact fullname="Toerless Eckert"/>, <contact fullname="Lars       Eggert"/>, <contact fullname="Reese Enghardt"/>, <contact fullname="Stephen Farrell"/>, <contact fullname="Simone Ferlin"/>,
      <contact fullname="Wes Hardaker"/>, <contact fullname="Jana Iyengar"/>,
      <contact fullname="Mallory Knodel"/>, <contact fullname="Dirk       Kutscher"/>, <contact fullname="Mirja Kühlewind"/>, <contact fullname="Allison Mankin"/>, <contact fullname="Alexey Melnikov"/>,
      <contact fullname="Marie-Jose Montpetit"/>, <contact fullname="Dave       Oran"/>, <contact fullname="Pete Resnick"/>, <contact fullname="Shivan       Kaul Sahib"/>, <contact fullname="Eve Schooler"/>, <contact fullname="Melinda Shore"/>, <contact fullname="Niels ten Oever"/>,
      <contact fullname="Brian Trammell"/>, <contact fullname="Rich Salz"/>,
      <contact fullname="Paul Wouters"/>, <contact fullname="Rod Van Meter"/>,
      and other members of the Internet Research Steering Group (IRSG) for
      their feedback on this code of conduct.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="authors-addresses" numbered="false" removeInRFC="false" toc="include" pn="section-appendix.b">
      <name slugifiedName="name-authors-address">Author's Address</name>
      <author initials="C. S." surname="Perkins" fullname="Colin Perkins">
        <organization showOnFrontPage="true">University of Glasgow</organization>
        <address>
          <email>csp@csperkins.org</email>
        </address>
      </author>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
